[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host jeff doolittle
i'm excited to invite felina as our
guest on the show today felina is
associate professor at the leiden
institute of advanced computer science
at leiden university
with a focus on programming education
she also works at the free university of
amsterdam where she teaches prospective
computer science teachers
in 2021 felina was awarded the dutch
prize for ict research
she is the author of the programmer's
brain a book that helps programmers
understand how their brain works
and how to use it more effectively it's
so great to have a fellow host
on the show as a guest welcome be here
thank you
well as i said in your intro your book
is titled the programmer's brain
is there something unique about the
programmer's brain yeah i don't think so
i mean i'd like to say yes right
because it feels so cool to have this
special brain that's different from
other people's brains
but actually recent research is also
showing more and more that
to be a good programmer you need to know
a variety of things or you need to be
able to do a variety of cognitive tasks
so there's a little bit of math
reasoning there's a bit of
language thinking there's also the
working memory
that you also use if you are looking up
directions to your favorite restaurant
or if you're reading
a difficult piece of non-fiction so it's
not that we have special brains maybe we
use
the different underlying cognitive
skills in a unique combination
but it isn't that great well hopefully
that's not disappointing to our
listeners to discover
but i imagine putting a brain that maybe
isn't unique
into different contexts than others
perhaps
lends itself to what you were just
saying there that our brains maybe
end up operating in different ways
because of the context and the kinds of
problems that we tackle is there
something to that
yeah it's definitely true that
everything you do often you'll get
better at
so it's definitely true that if you
program a lot like if you read lots of
java code then it will get easier and
easier for you to read java code
and there might be a little bit of
transfer to that this is a topic we talk
about the book
in the book as well so your knowledge of
java might transfer
to other programming contexts and
specifically if you think of c
sharp for example if you can really read
java well
probably you could also read c sharp
well the
farther away the programming language is
the less likely it is that
your knowledge is going to help you so
reading python already
is less likely to be supported by java a
bit and you might recognize
before but then there's another for each
that's a thing that we don't have in
python
and the blocks are different like where
are all the curly brackets
so the farther away a context is the
less likely
your prior knowledge can help you and
isn't it possible in some of those
situations that maybe we
think the correspondence is greater than
it actually turns out being
for example you mentioned c sharp and
java and
language transference or correspondence
there is one thing but then
you have to deal with the underlined
framework and so
can our brains trick us or maybe help us
in trying to distinguish
how much we really know versus how much
we just think we know
in a situation like that yeah so it's
definitely important to be aware of both
negative and positive trends so positive
transfer is if
your knowledge helps you because you
already know something but you also have
negative transfer
so i used to be a c-sharp developer and
then i became a python developer
and there was so much negative transfer
there because
like have you seen o-o in python so it's
like oh i'm gonna make a class
i know how to make a class let me just
define all the fields on the class
and then fight is like sure you can do
that in the constructor
i'm like but wait the constructor will
crash because i haven't put the fields
on the class so this was definitely an
example which i think is recognizable
for people also from other programming
languages
where you think you know everything but
you end up being wrong so i think the
most important
lesson is to all as always like check
your assumptions
so know that there is sometimes a
benefit and sometimes
a hindrance of prior knowledge don't
assume
that things are similar because it isn't
always and there are
so many different programming languages
and as you say it's not just about
syntax it's also about
how does the runtime work like.net and
the jvm have some
subtle differences even though the
programming languages
java and c-sharp are syntactically you
say they're almost the same
but then they're underlying ideas like
checked exceptions in java for example
that are even quite different from what
you might expect
absolutely so you mentioned just a
minute ago
positive transfer negative transfer are
those actual terms in the realm of
cognitive science
yes okay and then this is actually a
perfect segue because
i was about to ask you what about our
brains can make programming difficult
and we just hit on one
and it reminds me of a quote from
richard feynman it's one of my favorite
quotes ever and
it's the first rule is not to be fooled
and you're the easiest person to fool
and that sounds like a good summary of
kind of what you're saying there does it
also relate to cognitive science say you
know i i think a lot of our listeners
might be familiar with dunning-kruger
and i can put a link in the show notes
for those who aren't
and the best summary i can give it is
that low competence and experience often
leads to
high confidence is that related somewhat
to what you're describing
yeah so somewhat so i'm not really an
expert on
that but it is indeed the case that
sometimes people that really know
nothing
think that they have a very good
understanding how everything works
and it could be somewhat true that if
you step into a codebase in a
programming language that you're
unfamiliar with that you think oh
this is going to be easy i learned the
other language so this will be easy as
well
if you take that as an opportunity to
learn then everything's fine but if you
take that as an opportunity to
correct other people because you already
know how everything works then
you might fall in the trap right
and also that desire to correct others
leads me back to that feynman quote
where
instead of us thinking everybody else is
the easiest person to fool
maybe as part of recognizing our human
brains is starting and asking maybe i am
the easiest person to fool
and that's definitely what we talk about
in the chapter about transfer is just
be aware that around every corner
there might be another programming
concept that is slightly different
from how you learn it earlier can we
train our brains
to rather than settling for the dopamine
hit we get
of that excitement of oh my gosh this
works like i thought it would
and instead sort of you prepare
ourselves to be
excited for what's next like oh i
learned this but now
this excites me that maybe there's
something else i don't know that i can
learn
is that something we can improve at or
is it just never going to be that easy
yeah it's likely never going to be this
easy and that also has something to do
with how your brain works so your brain
is
always trying to save energy because
your brain is an expensive thing
in your body so where possible your
brain is going to rely
on your long-term memory rather than on
your short-term memory so short-term
memory is what comes into your brain
through your senses
and long-term memory is what you already
know and i think we all know these
nice examples of headlines with a typo
right and then you're like how could
people be so stupid how could they not
know this that there's a typo
right there i actually accidentally in
the first chapter of my book i put in a
typo and a few people are emailing me
like oh there's a typo there
but we put in the typo because it is
likely that many people
didn't notice the typo we put it in the
method called main
so that's something you've seen so often
so rather than
actually read the individual letters in
a main method
you look at the structure of the code
and you assume
oh that's probably me and they're like 2
000 people already bought my book
and 10 people sent me an email about the
typo
so i'm just going to assume that many of
the other people on my video were too
lazy
but many of the other people were indeed
just fooled by the typo where the
long-term
memory takes over and that's because
it's easier for you
it's way easier and cheaper for your
brain to assume oh that's the main
method oh that's a for loop
rather than actually reading the code
letter
by letter or character by character
that's slow
and in most cases it is needed because
so often your brain actually
exactly is correct right your long-term
memory tells you oh this is what it is
and that is what it is so your brain
wants to do better matching your brain
wants to save
energy by looking at unfamiliar
information and connecting it to things
you already know that's what the brain
was
made for so new information overruling
prior information that you already know
is always going to be hard
because it's expensive for your brain to
learn new things it's way easier to not
learn new things
sadly right right so we're always going
to be working against that but i think
recognizing that alone you know can
perhaps help us
even if we have to have external
constraints that are even possibly
self-imposed they can remind us about
these things about hey our brain wants
to be lazy
and it doesn't want to expend excess
energy which that just makes sense from
an evolutionary standpoint right it's
conservation of energy
so our brains are part of the universe
and therefore they are
beholden to the laws of the universe
what else about our brains can make
programming difficult in general
so what also makes it difficult to
program well i think is indeed
this interplay between the short-term
memory you have to
remember many things so if you're
reading unfamiliar code you just have to
remember
the method name the arguments what are
the concrete parameters
what class is this in what domain am i
working on
so that is known to overload your memory
and we know from cognitive science that
your short-term memory
can only hold five or six items more or
less
so as soon as you read a method with
many arguments
then this is going to be heavy on your
brain
and then it isn't just your short term
your short term memories for remembering
but you also have your working memory
and your working memory
is for thinking so in addition to
remembering many things
you also have to sometimes calculate
right so there's a pointer and it's
moving in the array
oh now it's at the first element oh then
it goes to the last animal
so you also have to puzzle information
together
so the fact that those two memory parts
the short-term memory
remembering information and familiar
information
and also processing and thinking that
that has to happen at the same time
that interaction is something that makes
programming really hard
but again this is also something that
makes reading non-fiction really hard
right
if you're reading a good paper article
about the topic that you're not so
familiar with like they
found a new type of rna or something
then
you're doing the same thing so we have
to remember the name of the scientists
and the university and oh what exactly
is the study that they did
so in a similar way piecing information
together in the working memory
is something you do in other contexts
also that makes sense
when you describe it that way it sounds
exhausting and
yeah i think that is probably very in
some ways relieving to our listeners i
know it is to me
because you know i recall hearing things
from other people
along these including family members you
don't really work
you just type on a computer all day but
what you just described is a high energy
system
within our bodies and in order to do
these tasks with heavy cognitive load
actually bears a cost and it could lead
to exhaustion
is there something scientifically to
that
well we definitely know that the brain
takes lots of energy from your body so
it is that if you're doing cognitively
demanding work
like reading or writing or whatever then
it needs it just takes energy again
that's very true so it's not weird if
you're exhausted yeah that makes sense
i think we've hit on some but maybe more
generally can you sort of describe for
us some common intellectual challenges
that coders
often face you know besides say fooling
ourselves with a model that doesn't
quite match or
overlooking a typo which i'm gonna guess
you put that typo in there on purpose
just as a demonstration of how the human
brain and the programmers brain
specifically works
but what other common intellectual
challenges are there that we should be
aware of as coders
so i think one challenge that's specific
to programming because the ones we just
described are somewhat generic
is that you just set cognitive load so
let me define that for people that might
not be
too familiar with it and dive deeper as
well so cognitive load the easy
description is
how hard your brain is working just is
this really hard
so that's so easy but in the book we go
a bit deeper
into different types of cognitive loads
so there's firstly
intrinsic cognitive load which you can
describe in programmers terms like
inherit complexity so if you are doing
binary church
for example yeah that's just a hard
thing
to visualize like oh you have to listen
you go to the middle and go to that side
or traversing a tree or also
thinking of databases in different parts
of the world
and they have to be eventually
consistent so you have to think of all
situations
something goes wrong oh is someone
outdated or someone offline
those type of situations are just hard
like that's inherent
intrinsic cognitive load is what that
creates but
there's also something called extraneous
levels and
extraneous loads is load that is
added to the problem that isn't
necessarily part of the problem and
here's the difficult thing
for program is that what might cause
extraneous load for me
might not cause extraneous load for you
so if we have
a distributed database system if this is
written in python for me that doesn't
give me
extra loads because i already know
python but if you're a java programmer
and you're helping me work on this
distributed system in python
for you that adds extra extraneous
load because you have to read all the
weird stuff about oo and python
if you work together with multiple
people in a code base
then what is easy to read for me might
be
really hard for you to read or
what is easy to read for me now might be
hard for myself to read in six months
because we also forget
things so i think that's the real
challenge where you're looking at an
artifact that firstly has an inherent
complexity
that can be high can already cause
cognitive loads
but then different people have different
prior experiences and because of that
they experience different cognitive load
like if you have to read a poem in dutch
they'll be super happy for your marriage
because you have to
like look up every word in the
dictionary you can get there
you can do this but you have to look up
every word and dictionary you know we
have these
weird words that maybe look like an
english word but then they're not
so it isn't that programming is hard
in general well it is but then also in
a team different team members might
experience
entirely different types of cognitive
loads
so something that we describe in the
book that can actually help with that a
bit is the the idea
of refactoring for cognitive processing
and i've started to call this
cognitive refactoring so if i'm
new in a python codebase and there's
lots of list comprehensions
and i'm a java programmer then with
every list comprehension i mean
what is happening here you have to use
your finger and look at the code like oh
this is this oh the if is there
so for you as someone new to that code
base you might just want to refactor
a bunch of those list comprehensions
temporarily to for loops just because
those are easier for you to process
or you might if you have this very
interconnected code base
that other people in the team are
already familiar with but you're new to
the team
not necessarily to the programming
you're new to the team and every method
calls another method on another class
maybe for you temporarily you might want
to inline
a bunch of methods so you can get the
sense for what is there
maybe some people are not like screaming
at their phone or at their computer like
no but then
you'll be making the code page worse if
you remove it just go branch no
yes just calm down and this can be
temporarily for that person and the nice
thing is
we have the technology to do this i can
be on my own branch
of the code and i can inline a few
methods and i can rewrite a few
things so that i gain a better
understanding of the code and i can just
be in the branch and do other useful
things
i can easily roll it back but we really
have to
step away from this idea that a code
base
can have code quality because then i can
say well jeff
look at this beautiful dutch poem why
don't you like this
it's so beautiful and deep this is
also of course to a lesser extent than
natural language but this is the way
we've been approaching code quality
like there's one thing one code base
that will be ideal for everyone
and of course there's some stuff that's
great for everyone like multiple linear
variables a b
and c and x 12. that's just helpful for
no one but some
constructs can be useful for you as an
expert in the domain
in programming language in the code base
but it can be really harmful for
beginners so this idea of
cognitive refactoring is you take code
and you make it
closer to what you already know and then
it's easier for you to process
and i think maybe for some people in our
industry that can be difficult because
oftentimes the sense is given that
coders should just code
and i tell coders and developers that i
mentor i say
if you're actually coding the code
that's going to be
the code okay you might be fiddling
around or things like you're saying
but if you're spending more than 20 of
your time doing that you're probably
doing something wrong because
the 80 of your time should be improving
your craft it should be doing things
like you're describing moving the code
around
seeing how it works knowing you're going
to throw this branch away
or interacting with product owners
interact with project managers
interacting with colleagues
making sure you have the right solution
before you write the code
or know that you're just exploring the
space in order to see what code you
might write so
i think it's quite interesting because
we actually described a little bit about
that in the book as well that
if we say programming we probably mean
a large variety of different tasks so in
the book we describe a number of
different
activities like sometimes you are
exploring
program like programming in exploratory
fashion this is
i want to have a new feature but i don't
know how to do it
and maybe i sketch out bits on paper but
i also go to my ide and i sketch
there i create a class and i create some
methods
and i write a few tests like this is
what i want
and this is very intangible right you
just want to
see how it feels i was just working on
our programming language and we have
this two-step model and when i was first
writing that
i didn't know if i wanted to have a to
like if i wanted to do
parsing and then transpiling or if i
wanted to do the whole way in one go i
didn't know
of course i knew what i want more or
less but i was like i just want to try
out
like what happens what will the
interfaces be if i try a two-step model
versus a one sample that's
exploratory programming and that might
be in a branch that you travel away
which is a very different type of
programming activity from what a model
that we described cognitive dimensions
calls transcription so transcription
is i have a plan i exactly know what i'm
doing
either because this task is really easy
or because i
charted it out on paper or someone did
that for me and the only thing i'm gonna
do is i'm gonna go into the code base
i imagine you have an off by one error
it's like oh
i know you see the error message yeah i
know what's up
you go to the right place in the code
you go there you fix the bug and you're
done
you see how different those activities
are and both
are programming of course even they're
both creation they're i'm not even
talking about reading code which is yet
another different activity but those two
activities
place so many different constraints on
your brain
on your workspace like do i need a
whiteboard do i need a keyboard
but also on your programming language
and your ide so if you distinguish these
different activities
as we describe them in the book then you
also get a better sense of what am i
doing
and you can have what i hope if multiple
people in a team read the book
then you get also the shared vocabulary
so you talk about a new feature
and then someone might say okay but are
you going to implement this in the
transcription way like do you know where
you're going
or do you want to explore this maybe we
can explore it together
so if we say programming we really mean
a bunch of
very very different activities that are
all cognitively
very very different from each other
there's a wonderful thinking tool
at least that's what i would call it
called the kniven framework and that's a
welsh word
and i don't recall what it means but
i'll put a link in the show notes to
that because
how what you're saying maps to that is
the kunavan framework lays out these
what are called different domains
and the domains one is an ordered domain
and so when you say transcription i
think of oh well these are the known
knowns
and we do best practice but then there's
the complicated where it's well these
are the known unknowns and maybe there's
good practice and then you get into the
complex domain and now you're into the
unknown unknowns and now
you're trying new things you're
exploring you're trying to figure it out
and
i imagine that kind of framework can map
in some ways to what you're describing
and maybe give us one of those thinking
tools that we need to help us discover
how to attack some of these tasks
yeah yeah that's definitely true that
indeed for all the different tasks you
also need
different strategies to approach them
absolutely
so in general there's a lot of
foundational concepts in this book and
we've touched on a few
cognitive load short-term and long-term
memory
and i think an underlying one that we
haven't really directly tackled yet but
you address it a lot in the book is this
idea of confusion
before you were mentioning different
people might have different extrinsic
versus
i think it was intrinsic intrinsic and
extraneous
ah thank you intrinsic and extraneous
that makes me think
of when we talk about human freedom and
the things that have held some people
back that we're trying to free them from
it it almost sounds like
intersectionality of your brain right
intersectionality
and sociology is the idea that somebody
who has
historically been oppressed in one way
may have other factors that cause them
to even have multiplicative effects
on things that have made life more
difficult for them in ways
and given them challenges that others
don't face in an expanding level right
not just additive but multiplicative
is that true here as well does that same
kind of concept apply this some of these
things we have one and then we have
another and it's not
just additive in its difficulty this is
even like expanding
the complexity and the difficulty of
what we're dealing with yeah i really
really like the angle that you take here
i think this is very true so what we
described in the book is that we talked
about these three memory systems
long-term short-term and working memory
and in the introduction of the book i
described that those
give rise to different forms of
confusion
so long-term memory confusion is if you
don't know something
like there's a key word and you don't
know it something like
a list comprehension in python you're
like why is the if at the end what does
this do
that's confusing but that is solvable
with more information
whereas this confusion of the short-term
memory where you have to remember many
things it's like oh
i have to hold everything in my head
this is the moment where if someone
your spouse comes in and like hey honey
do you want a coffee you're like
fire out of your eyes not no
not now that's also confusing you have
the concentration but that
you see that there's no confusion that
you can solve with extra information
this is confusion that you can solve
with training best practices
and then there's a working memory where
your confusion is
like what is what's what goes where and
maybe you can
understand all the syntactic elements
maybe you can remember everything
but you have to piece everything
together and that's yet another form of
confusion
and what we see with people that come
into programming or coming to a code
base
or a programming language is indeed it
adds up
so i go to kotlin that i've never done
before
now i don't know the contents i don't
know the syntax
i might not be aware of some of the
constructs like the fundamentals of the
programming language and then imagine
i'm doing an
iphone app and this is a domain i've
never done before i don't know the names
of the frameworks
i really have no clue what's going on so
indeed if you just have
one confusion one dimension is fixed
like you know all the syntax
and it's not so terrible if your working
memory is thinking really hard
but then if it's n and n indeed then it
isn't just
a bit of cognitive load here and a bit
of cognitive load there
then it's just it's just
and you get stuck and the sad thing is
of course that for some people
getting stuck and being confused leads
to in young people and people that are
learning
needs to oh program is really hard
maybe i don't want to be a programmer
and it's sad if we lose people just
because they don't know that
we can solve that confusion and that it
is indeed
it's not a terrible situation it's just
three things together and some others
maybe as well that together form this
this horrible confusion but these are
individual things that can be solved in
different ways
your passion is evident there and i
think it's wonderful that you're an
educator and not just of college
students for
university students from what i
understand but also for high school
students is that correct
yeah yeah that's correct i teach both at
university i teach at two universities
and also at one high school
and what a great opportunity for you to
help those students encounter what you
just described and tell them
it's gonna be okay it doesn't mean that
your brain doesn't function
or that you're less than or whatever it
might be
you know especially in an industry that
at times has it may be more than at
times but has had
situations where people who don't quote
unquote get it right away
sometimes they're downplayed or not
included or
pushed aside yeah that's very true so
there's this video of me
of a talk that i did at strange loop
2019 where i have some screenshots
from programming for children books and
they are
so much filled with like yay pain
is great and there's this screenshot
where it says like
if you learn programming this will be
confusing and it's going to be
frustrating and sometimes you will fail
like this is for 10 year olds right it's
gonna be frustrating you will fail
and you just learn by trying out things
which
i mean trying hard things isn't terrible
but if you have no
idea what's going on then what can you
try
i think that's one of the biggest things
that i really learned from
from teaching in high school more than
from teaching in the university
mainly because high school students they
tell you if they're confused
they tell you if something is
unreasonable whereas university students
are more like oh this is hard well
they've already learned it's about them
they're like oh well
maybe i'm not that smart but the 10 year
old 12 year old will just say
i don't understand this what is this
unreasonable this one student said to me
that a syntactic element in python she
said
this is unreasonable and this was
actually about
list comprehensions where in the for
loop
at the end of the for loop in python it
needs to end with it with a colon
and that's mandatory so i train them
colons colons
so they're like oh four don't forget to
call them they learn that
and then i teach them list go for
engines it's really nice to make lists
and to filter data
but then it starts with a four and it
doesn't end with a colon
and she's like but this is a reasonable
and i was like
you're right sister this is unbelievable
right
why is there a color here and not there
so that's i think the thing that
you take away that if you're an expert
and senior programmer might recognize
this if they're on boarding
more junior people i had never thought
about that because i don't even see
the goal i don't even see the brackets i
just see the concepts
but if you're learning yeah then it is a
bit unreasonable
that there are these syntactic
differences like third grader so
that's 14 15 year olds in the
netherlands first we did by phone and
now we're doing sql
they have to integrate sql queries into
a python program
and they're also like but why is it
different why is it capital letters now
why is it the star why is prince it's
all so
weird and that's i think so wonderful
because
you forget how hard it is if you're old
because it's so long ago
it's true and that's true in almost
every day or in every domain i mean as a
musician i have to remind myself that
people who haven't played you know an
instrument for as long it's going to be
hard for them learning and i think
that's one of the great reasons
to teach you know you do this you
professionally teach
but for us as software developers and
engineers to be teaching as well and
giving people that freedom and
you know ironically the teacher always
learns more than the student so
you know one of the reasons that you've
gotten where you are felina is because
you are learning more than your students
are
yes yeah
our friends at log dna are super tuned
into the devops space
they've taken feedback from devs ops and
security teams to create a log
management platform that gives users
access to the information they need
where they need it check them out
they're offering a fully featured 14-day
free trial to sc radio listeners
visit now.logdna.com
se to start yours today and see what all
the hype's about
[Music]
i want to go back to something you said
before because you're not just giving us
the programmer's brain
you're giving us a life lesson when you
say you're going to fail
and it's going to be okay and you're
going to learn and you're going to try
again
i think that message just needs to be
given loud and clear
not just to kids but as you mentioned as
we get into college and later into life
there's so much freedom in that it's i'm
not going to be perfect i'm not going to
have all the answers i'm going to need
others i'm going to need their knowledge
and experience and it's okay
would you say that's a mindset that
you've discovered is helpful
or even maybe even i don't know if it's
required but can
sort of set our programmers brains free
to be more productive
well i think the biggest thing that you
can do is so i wouldn't say too much
like lean into the struggle too much
because if you're struggling something
might be wrong
so right i would rather say this is also
what i say to students both at the high
school level and at the university level
if you're confused don't be stressed and
upset but do try to learn something
there
so what we often see in programming
culture is that we celebrate this
confusion
to the point where people are just
confused all the time
and they're not fixing it and so
something for example that we really
celebrate in programming culture is not
knowing syntax
it's like oh i don't know that i can
just google the syntax
and then this is true but is it really
effective wouldn't it be and this is a
rhetorical question
wouldn't it be way more effective if you
spend two minutes every day for one
month
to memorize the syntax this is going to
save you
so much time so if you encounter a
programming concept and
oh what is this and you are tempted to
look it up
why look it up every time look it up
once and memorize it
because the sad thing about our brain is
actually that if you look it up
instead of trying to remember it then
your brain will never learn
your brain this is really interesting
your brain actually
strengthens if you try to remember
something
even if you don't know it and you have
to look it up later
just trying to remember something is a
really strong way
to strengthen your memory this is called
retrieval practice
trying to remember something so if you
keep struggling with something
then you can say oh javascript is stupid
because i have to each time google
if it's set to equal signs or three
equal signs i can't remember this
because travel trip
is terrible yes you can also say okay
let me take a piece of paper i write
down once what is the difference between
these concepts and then you practice
averaging with your phone or on a piece
of paper
if you do just for a minute every day
for a while
you can actually learn so this is more i
think my message to kids and to
programmers that
if you're confused do something about it
and if it's confusion at the long term
memory level because you don't know
something you don't remember it
you can use flashcards this technique to
practice your long-term memory
if it is your working memory then try a
cognitive refactoring
put the code in such a form that it's a
bit
easier or we have lots of other
techniques in the book as well
like use some specific diagrams you can
help to support your
memory so yeah of course you're gonna be
confused but if i'm sometimes confused
if i read the newspaper as i said if
it's about the topic i don't really know
so it's fine if you're confused it's
nothing to be scared about
but it's also not something you should
accept as a given
there are things you can do to minimize
your current and future confusion
yeah it's when you've seen that same
stack overflow article three times in
the last month that you should probably
stop and say maybe i should work on
memorizing this
yeah or the most terrible form of that
is actually if you google something and
then you go to
your own blog or your own research
how do i know the remember this is that
number
you don't always have the mind space to
reflect but i really try to reflect more
and more if i've forgotten something
that i wrote myself
why does that and because some things
also they stay in your memory
when you use them often and if this is a
technique you haven't thought about for
a long time it's so this is
your brain trying to be helpful it sort
of drifts away
and things you have more recently
thought about many times
are a little bit more likely to actually
show up in your memory or things of
course like your spouse's name that
even if you don't use it a lot it's just
always there because it's really
important to you
so you have to reflect on like why did i
forget my own stack overflow post or
blog post like haven't i worked on this
technique for a while
why is that and especially if it then
turns out to be useful a bunch of times
in a row then it's definitely something
you want to explore and work on
well let's move on to another topic in
the book because i think
this is going to draw a lot of listener
interest
once they grab a copy of your book speed
reading for code
i mean that just sounds like the magical
tool you need to solve all of your
problems with confusion
and getting things done quickly so let's
start with
i mean i think it's kind of obvious but
as someone who's studied in this area
why is it helpful to be able to read
code quickly like i say it may seem
obvious but
maybe there's more of the cognitive
science behind this
yes there's not more of the cognitive
science behind it of
why is this useful right okay in the
book
that we spend we professional developers
spend
about 60 of their time on actually
reading code so reading code is a skill
you do a lot
and you do this in a variety of ways
right sometimes it is reading your own
code because you haven't worked on it
for a while or
reading a library on github that you're
like oh maybe i want to use this
in my project let me just see more or
less what is here
so there are different forms of reading
code but it's
always really really hard to read code
so if you get better at it
then yeah you'll be a more effective
programmer because you can read more
code
at a glance and so you say we spend 60
of our time
reading code when we're in the code and
that makes sense you have to understand
what you're looking at before you can
work on it or at least we all hope that
you attempt to do that before you
make changes to the code base you
mentioned before
and this it kind of triggered something
to my mind that it's
when you go to do a get blame and you
discover that it was you
yes and again it's that well that code
was out of sight out of mind it moved on
so to some extent it reminds me of what
i call the homer simpson rule which is
the don't hate your future self rule
there's homer simpson with a bottle of
vodka and a jar of mayonnaise and marge
basically says homer i'm not sure that's
such a good idea i can't do a marge
impression
and homer says oh that's no problem
that's a problem for future homer
boy i don't envy that guy and proceeds
to consume the vodka and mayonnaise and
you can imagine that probably didn't go
so well for him
so let's talk about i mean speed reading
obviously is important but i imagine
that's somewhat related as well to
readability and code
meaning is it easier to speed read code
that is more readable
and then how do we make that code more
readable for ourselves our future selves
and also for other people who may have
to interact with or maintain this code
in the long term
yeah that's a great question so i'm
going to try like answer
two questions at once like how do we
speed read and also how do we write
code that is easier to speed read
because it's speed readable yes yeah
let's be readable
it sort of comes down to the same thing
and we have to go back to that pattern
matching that i talked about earlier
that we talked about the book in more
detail
and this pattern matching actually in
cognitive terms we usually call that
chunking so chunking is if you
look at information and instead of
looking at individual elements
you process the whole thing at once so
if you read
english then you aren't if you're a
proficient adult
you aren't going to do like c-h-e-o
you just immediately see the programming
brain that goes at once
so there's lots of code structures of
course that
also lends itself to being chunked
and the interesting thing we talk about
this lots of deaths in the book
the interesting thing is that experts
people that are
expert in something really use their
long-term memory
very very extensively so we do these
experiments in which we have beginners
and experts remember code maybe some of
you that follow me on twitter i've seen
that we were
recruiting subjects the study was we
give you java you have to memorize it
and what you see in those studies not
just in programming but also in
board games and natural language is that
experts tend to remember
a lot more code in a short period of
time than beginners
and this isn't because experts have
extensive memory
that is because you break up the
information in small pieces so if you
have to remember
five for loops then you could probably
do that because you're not going to
remember
four i in range zero comma
five closing bracket colon you just
think oh
well the loop the iterator is i it goes
from zero to five it prints i okay next
one oh
here it is counter it goes from zero to
ten oh it prints reverse
you can easily process the information
not because you're a good information
processor
but because you've seen for loops many
many times
so the trick in speed reading is to
learn a large vocabulary of different
trunks
so practice and i have no no great
answer like oh this is going to be free
right oh you're going to be a great
speed reader tomorrow without any work
no
sad you have to put the work in but if
you have a large variety of
different chunks in your long-term
memory then you can read
code more easily and you can practice
this in yourself
also by doing this exercise of trying to
remember code
to just take random snippets from your
code base you put your hand on it
you try to reproduce the code what you
can reproduce
is the biggest chunks will be from your
long-term memory
because you can easily remember five
lines at once if it is a for loop or
if it is an api call that you use very
often then you're not gonna
think system points and then you're just
gonna remember the whole thing at once
so if you have this large vocabulary of
chunks
then it will be a lot easier for you to
quickly
read code because you aren't gonna do to
do you can just
read the whole block at once so that is
my tip for reading
going back to your other question like
how do you read code that can easily be
chunked
once you are aware of this idea of
chunkable code
you can use that in code so you know
that something like a for loop a while
loop a null check is this variable null
if so access it
is this connection database connection
open if so query it
those are recognizable blocks so you
want to use those blocks and put them
for example
put a white space above them so you can
easily see this is a block of code where
i think oh
this is what someone will use we also
talk about another technique in a book
called using beacons and beacons
are things that make people think of a
certain chunk so
the word for for example in in a for
loop can be a beacon if you see the word
for you know what's coming
or something like a null check you see
like if it's no
you're like oh now i know so you can
deliberately leave
beacons comments by the way can also
serve as beacons
it's recognizable it's like this warning
sign like warning
a recognizable trunk is coming so if you
have this vocabulary you can use it
because it makes you read code quicker
and
also you can use it so that you can
structure your code
in recognizable blocks and it can also
be the case that
in a team yeah we talk about teamwork
also in the book in the team that some
people use one form
of itching some people always use in
javascript edit they just explicitly say
oh if this is null then do this and
other people use this to ampersand
operations where it's like oh if this
isn't
null then i can access the other side of
the enzyme
those are chunks for this different
forms for the same
thing so it's not great for your brain
if
it alternates if the whole code base is
filled with this style and that style
and i think we talk a lot about code
style and systematic code style in terms
of
layout so we all want to have the same
layout many ides also fix this for us
there's many other dimensions that we
talked about in the book as well like
these synonyms so to say in code if
people use different synonyms
then they can all abide to the same
style but then
it's still very hard for your brain
where you have to switch with oh this is
an
explicit null check oh this is the
implicit version it's just
extraneous load also in terms of
variable names and we talk about camel
case versus
snake case it's nice of course if you
you use fab 8 and it's all the same
but there are other things about also in
the book like if you're calculating
the maximum interest rate is that going
to be
interest maximum maximum interest max
of interest and we often see that in
code bases these different
styles there's extensive research on
that i'm super excited not my research
i'm super excited that we talk about
that in the book called
name molds so what mold does your name
fit in and you see in the code base if
you have max interest
interest max max of interest if you have
all these different forms then you could
say oh you know this is bad eight
because
it's all the same we use gamma gay or we
use snake as on the variables and
camelca from the classes so
we have the same style but that is
surface style if you go to the cognitive
level
you also want to have it easy for your
brain to make it easy for your brain to
chunk a variable name and if the
information
sometimes is at the beginning and
sometimes at the end you can imagine
that impedes my speed reading because
then i'm reading like
so both at the beginning and so they're
all these things that we talk about that
it's just going to make
code easier for your brain to process
but again
one of the reviewers of the book said
yes but this is hard because then
me and my teammates have to make a
decision on how to structure names
yes friend i'm sorry i have no better
news for you yeah
it's the second law of thermodynamics
there's no value without sweat so you're
going to have to work for it and that's
just the way the universe works
yeah you know as you're talking i have
this thought in my mind and
listeners can't see us i wish they could
see you know when you did the head
explode sound before your hands doing
the actual motion
full disclosure i have no vested
interest in github whatsoever
other than i love it as a tool and so
many of us do but you know as you're
describing this i recall early days of
trying to learn
link in c sharp and link stands for
language integrated query and it's
basically something that microsoft
created to allow you to define
things like a sql query but using c
sharp code and it's not just for sql
queries but this is one example
you mentioned before your students
trying to learn sql while they're trying
to learn python and they're complaining
about the differences and this is crazy
and one of the really helpful things for
me in those days were refactoring tools
that allowed me to shift
because link has two views to it there's
a one that looks more like sql
it's not exactly see what is closer and
there's another one that uses method
chaining where you say you do a method
say dot where and then you put in a
where clause and then you say dot select
and then you put in your select clause
and
i preferred the method chaining method
but i couldn't comprehend it as well
at first and so now back to what i was
saying about github or other tools
online it
it seems to me there's a space for tools
that would let you look at the code
in a view that is more conducive to the
way your brain works
personally while allowing the team to
still standardize on something that may
not be your personal preference and then
instead of forcing you to adopt the
team's convention
the tool the source code host the ide
could give you the your view to reduce
your cognitive load while reading
but then if you have to modify it or
even convert it for you when you're done
i don't know it just seems to me there's
a space for that so maybe github or vs
code they can get on that
yeah that would be great i thought about
this idea a lot and i
thought about implementing a demo
actually but then i ended up
implementing other things
if you are listening people that make
programming tools this would be
tremendously useful and not just for the
scenario of
onboarding someone so they can look at
their version of the code but also
earlier in the show we talked about
different activities
so if i'm reading code i probably want
to have small
methods that are very like everything is
attracted because that makes
organization easier but then if i'm
working on code if i'm adding a new
feature maybe i do want to
inline everything for now because i
don't want to have like i'm debugging
and i have this web front end and then i
have three different classes processing
so i'm
stepping with my debugger because i'm
hinting for a bug and then it just hops
right
oh now i'm in the front end okay so the
code yeah let me quickly did the http
request okay they call me correctly okay
now i'm gonna go to that class oh now
it's pre-processed oh now it's first oh
now we go to the transpiler step
if i'm fixing something i don't want to
hop through three files every time
i think about your brain every time you
go to a new file
your working memory is like what your
short term memories oops i forgot
everything of the other file
oh gosh this is what you want to read of
course felina here's a fresh blank slate
to read this file so if you just for the
activity like of debugging the activity
of adding
fixing a feature you could say oh by
charm
and it doesn't have to be a given
feature could be an ide feature as well
whoever is managing my code inline
everything i don't care that i want this
in three collapse the stack and give me
everything top to bottom
in a linear view and if you wrote code
that way
that would be a procedural nightmare
because it's not maintainable
you know that's a great way of i think
in general we're exploring the space
which i know you spend a lot of time
doing as a researcher
but i guess the thought occurs me is
this they used to joke that programming
c
was basically just having an argument
with the compiler and it still feels
that way sometimes and
what i just felt like you were
describing was you know debugging is you
having an argument with your debugging
tools and who of us hasn't accidentally
you know told it to run when we meant to
say step over or step into and
oh and then you gotta restart your
debugging session yeah and not just
restart your debugging session from
your compiler has to do it right or your
items but also from your brain
because this is the working memory right
i've made my model of
okay so this is what happens oh but why
is this value
zero they should never be how can this
possibly be zero
and then you need to build your we talk
about mental models in the book as well
you build your mental model of how
everything is working
and then indeed accidentally you hit
step over instead of step into
and then it goes to the next line and
then your value isn't no oh now it is 12
like it's supposed to be okay so now i
know that's
but why why the somewhere in between
looking at someone that was born in the
80s ideas nowadays
are amazing right some ideas will let
you
actually i still think this is
mind-blowing go back in time
you take the print point you shift it up
and it goes back
i know how this works technically but it
still blows my mind that that is
possible
but not only is that possible and even
if it is possible
from an ide perspective from a cognitive
perspective this isn't free
because you're there and you're like oh
crap i have to go back and then your
brain is thinking about where do i put
the breakpoint
rather than about filling a mental model
of code so it would be spectacularly
cool if indeed just
it's not very hard just give me a this
is called a slice of code so a slice is
all the code that is related to the line
that i'm looking at so you could say
give me the slice of this code which is
everything
in the code base that relates to this
buff how cool would that become much
more effective would we be
if someone would build this for us that
would be amazing
in as you're saying this i'm even
visualizing the experience of being able
to still see the layers of the stack and
the methods and the classes
you know assuming what kind of language
you're in but having this sort of full
tool a while back and with a while i
think i mean a decade or something
it was called code bubbles and this is
an alternative
research ide that let you do something
like
that so instead of looking at classes as
files
you could make bubbles you'd have to
place them yourself but you could place
bubbles so you'd have one method and
then it calls the next bubble
next to it so rather than going to a
different tab in your ide
it would have the bubble next to it and
then the next bubble so you could make
this
call sac visual i don't know what we
maybe we could put it in the show notes
if it's still like i don't know what
happened to it but i do know it's
definitely not mainstream like all my
friends use
crazy studio code and not code bubbles
so i think so
right they stop working on it and then
even
oh yeah and then even layers of give me
full procedural
and i don't want any of that other stuff
and then i want to add a little bit of
that
all the functions i don't care about
what goes where i just want to see the
sectors
this speaks to you know you've talked a
lot about us humans as pattern matchers
and that absolutely is what we are and
not only of course but that's part of
what we are and we're also tool makers
and so
now that's kind of what we're exploring
here is how can we make our tools work
for us
yeah and as advanced as ides are right
now
to improve them to another layer this
would be great to see tool makers
start to explore a space like this where
we can have multi-perspectival
views over code different views for
different reasons i mean yeah we have a
debug window and we have a stack trace
and a watch and a locals and these
things
but you're still jumping from file to
file method to method and that adds
cognitive load
does it not definitely that adds
cognitive load definitely
so a little bit of cognitive load a
little bit of your working memory
is inevitably going to be spent
on remembering where you came from like
what method you went through
and because we have strong pattern
matches your long-term memory is always
in the back like imagine like you have
an angel on your shoulder always trying
to be helpful
so you're reading the name of a method
like it's maybe find customer right
your long-term memory is oh do you want
to find customers find customer
finding synonyms searching customers
database so it's trying to throw this
information at you that's relevant
and this is helpful all the time right
this is why we have a conversation
because you say something and i'm like
oh but that makes me think of so this is
very very useful but that is also
crowding your working memory
so if you have to see through class
names and function names that aren't so
relevant
for your current tasks your long-term
memory is trying to be helpful you have
to suppress it
this all goes subconsciously but
sometimes you have to
literally say this to something no no
stay on top
like no i have to think of what am i
doing so if you can
remove all the fluff that isn't
necessary for the current
task then yeah certainly that's that is
likely to make us
more effective if people are actually
going to implement this i can
run a user study so if you actually want
to know is this
is it i can do some observation studies
you heard it here
everyone who is involved with building
developer tools we want not a stack
trace
we want to see the linear procedural
the stack as code and be able to debug
it
and have it help us modify that code so
please get on that and we will thank you
for that
and you can contact felina if you want
to have her
include that as part of her research
this would be wonderful it would be yeah
here we are solving the world's problems
but then again until this exists
there are things you can do yourself
right of course okay look very
cumbersome
to put everything in this inline
everything yourself oh gosh
yeah but as a technique of course this
is something you can in line a bunch of
methods so i hope that
what people take away from this apart
from our creative ideas for ids that
they also take away that
sometimes it's okay to make code worse
so i really love this focus that as a
community we've been having on
craft person ship like we want to make
code better we want to hone our craft we
want to make codes
in a perfect state we want to have short
methods
short parameter lists i stand by all
this so don't go tweet like oh
felina hormones i hate readable code no
but
it has to be useful it has to serve its
purpose and sometimes it can be totally
okay
to inline a bunch of methods for now if
you feel that support in your working
memory if you are in this state where
continuously
you're hopping between files or between
methods because
there is a feature that is in both of
those methods
this might be a sign that maybe those
methods should be one because why are
you hopping
but also it is fine for now to just put
it in a state that you wouldn't commit
to help it support your working memory
then that's as i said this is what we
call in the book of cognitive
refactoring
that is okay don't worry about your
teammates saying oh but that's not a
proper form
it's just temporary to help you support
absolutely
let's make sure we haven't missed one of
the topics that comes up often in your
book
and i want to make sure we haven't
missed any bugs in our thinking
i think we've hit on a few but maybe
highlight them a little
more obviously these that we've
discussed before bugs in our thinking
and anyway we've missed that you want to
make sure that we
cover as well oh that's a great question
so there are lots of
detailed books in our thinking which in
cognitive terms are called
misconceptions
so misconceptions is not if you're wrong
or if you're unsure
you're wrong but you also are sure you
are right
and that's the most terrible form of
being wrong
so this is like in cognitive science we
talk about misconceptions for example if
you
explain something to a child a bunch of
times and still they have the wrong
idea about something and there's a
really nice i cite this in the book as
well a really nice psd thesis
by someone called juha sorva he wrote a
phd thesis and in this thesis is a list
of 107
programming misconceptions and this
thesis is available on the internet
so that is just not all the ways but
many many many different ways in which
people can be
wrong about programming so i could give
like 50 examples but the most important
thing i think that we did talk about
is this often happens if you transfer so
i'm just going to assume that everyone
that's a professional java programmer
probably they don't have java
misconceptions probably they know
how stuff works but then going to
another language
is where misconceptions happen and
sometimes also going to a different
domain so if you first you work in
finance and then you go work in
insurance
many words are the same like portfolio
for example
but that really might mean something
very different in trading
than it does in insurance an insurance
portfolio is different from a stock
portfolio
so that is also a situation if you
transfer to a new domain
where you might think oh i know
portfolio and then it's slightly
different it isn't of course something
entirely different
and that's why the trick is because it's
somewhat similar it is a collection of
things
you assume it will be the same and
that's where misconceptions happen so
they're very related also to
negative and positive transfer that we
talked about earlier in the book
absolutely and we'll put a link to that
phd thesis that you mentioned
in the show notes for listeners i
imagine you probably reference it in the
book as well yeah
actually we take out a few
misconceptions like for example a famous
example that happens if kids learn to
program
is that they think that a variable can
never be changed
and then you're like that is so weird
because it's literally called a
very good i would think that but then
this often happens with kids that have
extensive experience in math
because in math a variable isn't
variable
right it is variable in the sense that
in a proof you can define it at will
but it never changes you don't have a
mathematical proof
where you say it's all oh x is 12 and in
the middle of the proof you say
no x is 17. so people that come from a
heavy math background they come into
programming
and they read something that is x equals
x plus one and they're like but that's
false
because there's an x and it cannot be
equal to itself plus one
nothing is equal to itself plus one and
then this makes no sense
so that's just whoever decided equal was
the assignment operator i kind of want
to say couldn't we have had a different
assignment operator
yeah we should still have a different
assignment well it's too late now
it's too late well i don't know maybe
it's not but well can all make your own
programming language
but so that's the typical example you
also see the role of transfer
right no baby is born with an intuition
for what the equal sign means
first we put it in and then later we say
oh haha
now it's different different subject and
sometimes this is like very tricky
for high schoolers also for university
students they have algebra
where the equal sign is something
entirely different and also
like functions and we have functions in
math
are always immutable they take in
something and they return a value so
they're from algebra
at 9am and then the next hour i'm like
hey i'm defining a function in the
middle in python
i'm just assigning a value to this
global variable because
i'm the king of the universe so you see
that this continuous transfer between
topics with slightly
different interpretations and this of
course that isn't just
with university students also in the
code base
your front end and your back end they
might get different programming
languages
they might have slightly different
versions
sometimes in code bases especially if
they live very long
and there was a change in definition so
initially
we called something we called it the
parser and then later on we split this
into two different functions
and then one is also called the parser
so now we have parser print parser right
and that isn't great and we all know
it's not perfect but it just ended up
that way and like with the assignment
operator
everyone knows now that that's a bit of
a weird api call but that's how we do it
and then yeah newer places in the code
base they might have a
slightly different convention because
new people come in and they're like what
is this we'll do it properly
and then you switch between code bases
or between methods or classes
and stuff is certainly different and
just a little bit different
this is where bugs are conceived right
because you think
i know what this function does i know
what this concept does and it's
you're almost right but not entirely and
almost right can be very dangerous
yeah and that's in this interaction of
positive and negative transfer right
because in many places you're right so
this positive transfer gives you the
confidence that this last thing will
also be true and then that's where it's
not
well and that's great cause that comes
full circle to what we started with and
to kind of sum up that thought
we've explored humans as pattern
matchers
we've also explored humans as tool
makers and again tool makers you know
please do some of the things we talked
about in this episode
but now it occurs to me as well that
humans are storytellers
and that seems to be a big aspect of
this but i really appreciate how you
connected it with usefulness and i think
in all three of those areas
that's something that we ought to use as
an evaluative tool for how well is our
programmers brain serving us in those
three areas of pattern matching tool
making and storytelling is this
useful yeah and with that i want to go
to the hardest thing in computer science
which of course
those of us who know i'll put a link to
it in the show notes but right basically
there's only two hard things left in
computer science
cash invalidation naming things and off
by one problems
so let's talk about naming things what
makes a good name you know before you
mentioned
max of interest or interest max and of
course i'm thinking in my mind
somebody's going to want to call it max
int which would just be
sadly hilarious and painful so let's end
there
what makes a good name when we'll wrap
up the show after we kind of explore
this topic a little bit
in the book we describe different
perspectives so there are different
perspectives there's tension so you want
to have a name that is descriptive
that clearly explains what it's doing
which can be at
all to which you want to have a name
that is short because the shorter the
name
the quicker it is read and the easier it
is to
parse and to quickly process longer
names
just take more time but shorter names if
they're very short
also take a longer time to read there is
really nice research
that we cite in the book as well and the
title of the paper is shorter variable
names take longer to comprehend
which means nothing to the imagination
right so
shorter is not better but very long
isn't great either
so this is something sadly i mean we're
all engineers and we all want to have
something like
give us the magical formula so it is the
name of the concept divided by 17 plus
four and that's the ideal length
but there's no such thing as ideal
length so this will always be a trailer
but what we talked about before i think
that's one of the most interesting works
that i cover in the book is this idea of
name molds
that if you put names in the same
systematic
form that really support your pattern
matching brain
so you want to have this first this
discussion or the decision
what do i put in a name right what are
the relevant concepts
but once you've found that when you've
decided these are the things that matter
always put them in the same form and
this is very new research so it's really
like last year
so there hasn't been so much research
into what form is better what name mold
performs better
i hope that scientists will go that
direction but i think for now not
knowing what form is better
knowing what we know about the brain is
i would say it doesn't really matter
which one you pick
but pick the same one so invite the
bullet with your team
and decide okay what do we do do we do
noun first we do
verb first and this is what we do
throughout the code base where it's
relevant
that will be a process that takes a bit
of time easier for fresh code basis
harder
for extensive long little code bases
where your long-term memory
for a while will be like hey oh
that looks different i'm confused i'm
angry
so it will take a while before you get
used to the new variable form but i
think that's something that you can
really do what we know from cognitive
science just tells us
that if stuff is always the same your
brain will be like oh i know this
it's just easier than having to read and
figure out the variable
and it would be easy also in a sense
once you've made the decision which i
know is not easy it'll be easy to
maintain you can put in your readme or
github you could say okay this is the
name molds
that we use if many people read my book
this vocabulary
will be well known this is the name mold
that we use so you can just use it
everywhere in the whole base consistency
and standardization
are going to reduce that cognitive load
for sure and specifically consistency
cognitive consistently so not we use
snake case
which is definitely useful and it
already reduces loads of bits
but within a framework like using snake
age you still have
so much freedom of where the important
parts of the name go that you want to be
a little bit more precise
yeah and i'll just add it's fun to hear
you talk so much about python you
mentioned pep8 which of course we'll put
in the show notes it's a particular way
of formatting your python code and
there's tools that will
tell you if it's off and help you fix it
but then you've mentioned list
comprehensions you've mentioned snake
case and
for our python listeners out there they
recognize and fight hard for doing
things the pythonic way and so
congratulations on making the switch
from java and c-sharp oop and
actually embracing the way of python so
that's just fun to hear yeah and we'll
add links to all that in the show
in the last few years i've only been
both teaching and using
python for my own project so i think
that shows in the examples that this is
your long-term memory right
those are the examples that i thought
about most recently so in the heat of
the podcast it is easiest for me to come
up with these examples that are fresh in
my memory
yeah and that's great that you began
your career one way
and with a couple of languages in some
ways or even a different paradigm
there's
obviously some similarities but that's
just hopefully encouraging the listeners
as well
that it may seem daunting there's all
these new languages to learn
but it can be done and i think that
represents as well
that having a community and it's your
smaller community of your team how are
we going to do name molding and how are
we going to apply that
but the broader community as well that
adopting the principles of how they do
things
that can be another way to reduce your
cognitive load reduce your confusion and
help you be more productive
yeah definitely and i wish now in
retrospect that i had
already written and read my own book
when i was making the transfer because
in many situations
i was so so confused
and it's so hard if you're an expert
because i was like a good ccr programmer
so i was like it's just because i'm old
it's because i can't learn another
language
i will never learn this and it's just
because i like the techniques
to learn and i like the understanding
that the confusion i was feeling wasn't
i'm aging but was just negative transfer
hitting me in the face all the time so
i really hope that knowing about these
techniques and knowing about the
vocabulary
that you can say to yourself instead of
oh my god i'm stupid you could say
maybe i'm experiencing too much
cognitive load what can i do to manage
my own cognitive load that's really a
nicer
like inner conversation with yourself
then you're too old go back to c
sharp give up programming you will never
learn anything
yes it's an enabling thought rather than
a thought that shuts you down
or discourages you and we could do a
whole and this wouldn't be a software
engineering radio episode of course but
i'm sure a whole episode could be
dedicated to the
internal conversations we have with
ourselves that hold us back and
and how to overcome that as well but
your passion is evident
and it is clear that you just basically
said it you wrote the book that you wish
existed when you needed it and it didn't
so you wrote it and those to me
are often some of the best books you're
ever going to read
i hope so so if people want to find out
more about what you're up to where can
they go
well you can follow me on twitter my
first name is very unique in the world
so that's easy so my twitter is
at felina my website is felina.com and
where you can read also about all the
research i work on
and if you want to know more about the
book specifically you can simply go to
felina.com
where there's a link to the publisher
and some background information
also that's great and for listeners
that's felina spelled
f-e-l-i-e-n-n-e
falina so i'm very jealous and i'm sure
some of our listeners are that you have
one name and so you know you've joined
that club of celebrities
that are known for just the one name so
that's great thanks to my creative
parents that had this
oh no no but it's great and it helps
people find you and learn more about
what you do and clearly you're making
great contributions
both academically but also to those of
us who are practitioners and
professionals so
i'm so grateful thanks for joining me
today on software engineering radio
thanks for having me it was great to be
on as a guest for once
absolutely well this is jeff doolittle
for software engineering radio thanks
for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine
for more about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at
se radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on linkedin
facebook twitter or through our slack
channel at
scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening